Okay, let's get started. So, hi
everyone. My name is Yan. I'm a
researcher at OpenAI. Uh, and I'll be
re-recording a class that I gave um at
the Berkeley LM agents MOO series on
introduction to training LMS uh for AI
agents. So the reason why we're
recording this class is because one we
had technical difficulties uh early on
in the class and um second there was a
fire alarm that started um which means
that we did not go through all the
slides and also we don't have a good
recording and I want to make sure that
everyone who's online would also um see
the entire class. Um so before getting
started one thing to say is that all the
all views here are my own. uh even
though I work at OpenAI, I will mostly
talk um about things that we will we can
find online and information that we can
find of open source models, especially
Kim, Lama, and Deepseek. Um so unless I
talk about OpenAI, um nothing is related
to OpenAI here. Uh great. So with that,
let's get started. So we all know that
LM and chatbots really took over the
world in the last few years. So the
question I will try to answer is how do
we actually um train those? How do we
train those models? So this is an
example here uh from um from JGPD and
and an answer from JGPD.
So there are three main main uh parts of
the training pipelines uh when training.
The first one is pre-training. Uh so you
probably all heard about it. Uh the
general mental model that I like to give
people is that pre-training is really
about predicting the next word on
internet. So you take all of internet or
all the clean part of internet and you
just try to predict the next word and as
a result you will learn everything about
um the internet and as much as possible
about the world. Um in terms of data uh
pre-training takes more than at least
for the big models the big open source
models takes more than 10 trillion uh
tokens. So that's a lot when I say
tokens it's you can think a little bit
about it as words or like subwords but
essentially more than um 10 trillion
tokens. So think about it, it's like
10,000 words uh sorry 10 trillion words.
Uh it takes months to train on that much
data and it takes a lot of money uh and
a lot of compute to actually train on
that on that amount of data. Um so you
can think about the compute cost being
more than like 10 million for for one
run. Uh so here the bottleneck in
pre-training is both the data as we
talked about controlling is a lot and
second is uh is compute and as we will
see basically the more you scale up
these models so that means the more data
you put in the model and the the more
compute so the more uh the longer you
train for the better the performance
will be. So an example of pre-trained
model is like lama 3 for example.
So a second part which actually is third
in a chronological order of how these
models are usually trained. Um but this
is the second part that came uh after
pre-training. Um the last part is more
recent. Um so the second part is classic
what what I call classic postraining or
RHF so reinforcement learning from human
feedback. Here the idea is that this
pre-trained model is just good at
predicting the next word but it's not
really good at uh like performing well
in in the sense of predicting what the
user wants uh or predicting like
answering questions or like following
instructions. Uh it basically you can
think about it as a model that knows
everything about the world but it
doesn't actually know how to interact
with a human. That's one way of thinking
about it and that's what we're going to
try to optimize for is modest
interaction with humans and making sure
that when you ask it to do something it
does it. Um the data size here is much
smaller maybe around like a 100,000
problems. Um all these uh all these
numbers are are just orders of magnitude
and just to give you a sense in terms of
time it probably takes a few days to do
what? Yeah, a few days to do one of
these runs. compute cost maybe around
like a $100,000 uh dollars and here the
bottleneck is data and evos um so when I
say data I really mean the quality of
data because £100,000 is not that much
so it's really about high high quality
uh the data is and uh whether you know
what like whether you can um evaluate
whether you're making perfor um whether
you're making uh um
improvements on your run um so how good
uh you're improving your run. And this
is really important because when you do
this RHF or this this post training, you
have to balance many things together.
So, you need to make sure that you're
actually um tracking your performance on
all these all these different axes. So,
uh a spec like a specific instantiation
of this LHF model is a a lama instruct.
So, when you hear instruct at the end of
the model, that usually means that it
just went through all HF. Uh because it
can now do instruction following. can
follow instructions that are given by
humans. Great. And this last spot which
actually as I said uh usually comes
second in the pipeline is the reason
what I call the reasoning reinforcement
learning. Um so the idea here is uh to
think on questions where there's
objective uh answers or where you have
access to ground truth. Um so you will
hear recently um you will see hear from
from open source models also that like
perform very well on on math and like
coding and things where it's actually
pretty easy to get some ground truth
answers for example like passing test
functions in coding or like passing some
some math exam. Um and this is what you
what you want to optimize during this uh
reinforcement learning for reasoning. uh
so this second this second uh stage is
only true for reasoning models so one
example is deepseek R1 which was the
first reasoning or the first open source
reasoning model uh in terms of data um
so they don't in in the R1 paper they
don't say exactly but you can kind of
read through the lines um and and you
can look at the plot and try to extract
the uh around the amount of problems
that they're actually training on so in
terms of data it's probably around a
million
problems that they're training on
probably takes um in the order of weeks
to train uh this this second stage. So
this reasoning stage around a million
dollar and here the ball is
reinforcement learning environment and
hacks. So what I mean by that is as I
said this is about optimizing for
objective truth or optimizing for
example if you take the the the case of
passing test functions in coding the the
ball is how many test functions can you
get um and one thing that will usually
happen is when you start optimizing for
these test test functions or test cases
you will you will see that the model
will start optimizing things that you
weren't expecting. Um so maybe it will
be able to pass the test case by for
example removing the test in uh in your
environment or replacing it with always
returning true. That's like one of the
type of thing that the model may do. Um
which is what we usually call hacks. So
the the way to think about hacks is just
the model found a way of uh optimizing
the reward uh even though that's not
what you were hoping that it would do.
Um so so this is usually a pretty big
balling because um models are really
good at optimizing things um even if
it's not exactly the type of thing that
we want to optimize. If you if you write
something to optimize they will optimize
it exactly as written um and and usually
the second stage uh so sorry the second
and the third stage um I will bundle
them together and call them postraining
um which comes after pre-training. This
is it kind of depends. Different people
have different names. Um that's how I
believe R1 and and Kimmy uh talked about
that in the post training stage.
Great. Uh so the LM training pipeline.
There are basically five things um that
you need to consider when training an
LM. First is the architecture. So what
what model architecture are you using?
So you probably all heard about
transformers um or about mixture of
experts which is a kind of a variant of
transformers um and then there's a
training algorithm and the loss. So that
means how what are you optimizing for
this architecture to do? Um so what is
what are you trying to optimize?
Um and then there's the the data and the
all environment. So that's what we
talked about before. uh this evaluation
which is knowing whether you're making
any progress and then last part is uh
systems and and infra to make sure that
you can scale up these runs. Um so until
I would say 2023 most of academia was
actually focused on architecture and
training algorithm and and losses. Um
I've done also a PhD. That's what I was
focused on until around 2023. And and
really there were a few people who were
working on the rest, but that was like
the the main um yeah the main part of of
academic research. Um but in reality
what matters in practice is the last
three. So what matters is usually data
evaluation and systems to be able to
scale. So people usually want to work on
architecture on on like developing new
algorithm for for optimizing your model.
But these things matter much less as we
will see than really how much data do
you put in? What's the quality of your
data? Uh are you measuring your progress
well and do you have the infra to
actually scale things up?
Um so I will not be talking about
architecture. Um mostly because at this
point the architecture is not changing
that much in the open source. H so it
seems to be mostly using kind of
transformers with mixture of experts and
a lot of people like talking about
architectures. So you can find a lot of
information about what architecture is
being used. Um and as I said it's I I
think it's um at least currently it's
really not as important. Um so that's
why I will not be talking about that.
Okay. Um there's two last spots that I
didn't talk about in the kind of
pipeline for training LMS and that's I
consider them more about specializing
the LM. Um one is prompting. So once you
usually have a model for example a big
lab or big open uh yeah big lab might
might release a big open source model or
or closed model and then people will be
able to interact with it and and
specialize it uh that model for for
their use cases and the usual way that
people do it is first just by prompting.
Uh so prompting is really just um
knowing how to ask questions
essentially. So it's kind of the odd of
asking the model what you want. Um what
is nice is that you don't need any data.
Um and it's pretty fast. You just try a
few a few examples and you see how it
works. Uh there's kind of no compute
associated to it or very little. And the
bic is eval like how do you make sure
that you actually have a good prompt
that you're asking the right question to
the model. And then uh the second part
is finetuning. Um so we will not be
talking about it but just to mention it
here briefly. Um this is the fine-tuning
is basically continual
uh post training or or an additional
post training where you basically uh
apply the the second stage of post
training to domain specific data. So for
example, I imagine that all these models
so all these models actually release
pretty general uh sorry all these
companies release pretty general models
and now you want to specialize it to to
some specific specific domain like like
medical data. So you might have like
internally you might have or for your
project you might have some specific
data that you want to optimize for and
you will take these open source models
and you will be basically fine-tuning uh
so doing a little bit more of training
on your specific data. Uh and just like
post training this requires around like
maybe 10,000 to 100,000 problems around
days and like compute cost around like
10,000 to 100,000. And here again just
like post training the the ball is
really the quality of your your data and
evaluation. How do you know whether
you're making progress?
Great. Um so let's talk about
pre-training. I will talk about the
method what what pre-training is the
data and the compute that you need. So
in terms of uh pre-training the usual as
I said the mental model I I like the
metaphor that I like giving to people is
that uh pre-training is about predicting
the next word. Um and the way to think
about it is just for example when you
type a message uh you will usually see
your your phone like predicting what's
the next word that you will predict. And
this is exactly how pre-training works.
So or or not exactly but like mostly
this is kind of the the metaphor I like
giving and it's essentially how how
pre-training works. So the goal of
pre-training is to teach the model
everything in the world and the way that
we basically achieve that is just to
predict the next word because if you can
predict the next word then you must
understand if you can predict the next
word on every single domain then you
must have like some understanding of
that domain. Um
and and that is basically uh what
pre-training is. So in terms of data uh
it's basically any reasonable data on
internet as much as possible because you
really want to again you want to to to
have models that understand as much as
possible at everything. Uh so you really
want to give as much data as possible um
for the model to uh to learn on.
So in terms of scale of data you have
around maybe I said more than 10
trillion tokens. So for Lama 4 for
example, I believe the models were
trained with between 20 to 40 trillion
tokens. For Deepsec V3, I believe it was
15 trillion tokens. So it gives you kind
of a order of magnitude of data that you
need uh for current for the current best
open source models. Uh so that 10
trillion tokens corresponds to
approximately
20 billion unique web pages. Uh so
that's a lot of data. uh it's not all of
internet but it's uh it's basically all
the clean data that people can find um
on internet uh and pre-training has
really been the key since GPD2 uh in
2019 that mostly showed the world um
what pre-training can do and basically
just using a simple method like
predicting the next word but you just do
it at scale um it it really showed um
how how smart the models can become
okay so what is actually what is
actually happening under the hood. Um
I'll give you first a brief overview in
terms of task as I said it's about
predicting the next word. Uh so the
steps are the following. First you token
is tokenize the data. So here I have a
sentence she likely prefers and the goal
is to predict the next word. So in this
case the next word is dogs. So she
likely prefers. So what you will do is
you will split up she likely prefers
into different tokens which are
basically different subwords or
different subunits. The reason why we do
that is because computers I mean they
don't understand words they only
understand numbers. So you have to take
these words or you have to take this
sentence and uh and split it up into uh
into um into numbers. So that's what we
call tokenize. Uh so once you have um I
split I split it up by by word here. of
my space. So I have she likely prefers
and I say all these three three words
become tokens. Um and I will associate
all of these tokens with a different
index. So she I will give it one likely
becomes two and prefers becomes three.
Um this is just one way of converting
again these uh these words um that
computers don't understand to like
numbers that computers can work with.
Then you will you will do a what we call
a forward pass which means that you will
pass it through the model. We'll see
exactly what happens later but you will
pass it through the model. So usually
this is a transformer and then you will
have this model try to predict a
probability distribution. So a
categorical distribution that tries to
predict what is the probability of the
next word. Uh so for example here you
see that she likely prefers it's very
unlikely to say she again um but it's
very likely to say this word which in
this case is dog. Uh and then you will
sample from this priority distribution.
Um so once you have a model that
predicts a distribution you can just
sample and that's why every time you ask
a question to to uh to some open source
model it will not always get the same
answer because you actually have this
sampling step. um you sample and then
you detokenize because again when we
talk about it in um uh in this
categorical distribution that just tells
me that this is token number five here I
have 1 2 3 4 five I want index here so I
have five and then I need to look
through my dictionary that tells me
index five was actually the word dogs or
the token um dogs so that's ID tokenize
so the last two steps um this is not
super important but last two steps
that's only happening at inference time.
At training time, uh all you can do is
you can always keep predicting the next
uh word by predicting the probability
distribution and just optimize
optimizing your across century loss
which I'm sure most of you are familiar
uh with. So you don't actually need to
do the sampling. Um
so these two steps are only doing
inference. Great. Uh so now I want to
give you some intuition about why this
can even work. Um, and to do that I will
talk about honestly kind of the most
simple language model that you could
think about. Um, and this is the engram
language model which was uh already used
at scale in 2003. So like very long time
ago. It already worked pretty well. Uh,
but I think it gives a good intuition of
what is happening under the hood for the
current models. So the question here is
how can you learn what to predict?
because we talked about before I said oh
you just do a forward pass to your model
and just predict a distribution like how
can you learn that so one way uh you can
do uh that so let's take an example say
how can you know what comes after the
the sentence the grass is and you
probably know that after the grass is
it's most likely to be like green for
example so how can how can we know that
how can we teach them all to do that um
well the solution is statistics uh
statistics is always the solution to
most of your problems. Um, so one way
you can do that is you can take all the
occurrences of the sentence the grass is
online or for example take all the
occurrences of the grasses on Wikipedia.
Um, and now you can predict the
probability of every word that comes
after the grass is by looking at the
number of times that that word appeared
after the grass is normalized by the
number of time that you saw the sentence
the grass is. So let's say that like um
the the sentence the grass is happens a
thousand times on the the the web pages
that you looked at and maybe half of the
time so maybe 500 times uh the next word
is green and maybe uh like I don't know
a 100 time the next word is red um you
will have then probability of green
knowing the grass after the grass is
will be half so 500 divided by a th00and
and for red it will be at 10%. So 0.1.
So that's a very simple way of
predicting the the distribution the
categorical distribution of the next
word. Um but this would work. It would
actually work pretty well at least for
for simple things like the grasses. That
would actually work pretty well. Uh
there are still a few challenges. Um,
one is that you need to keep count uh of
all the occurrences for each of these
engrams or at least in this case each of
these sentences that happened. You need
to keep a count of every word that came
after. Uh, so just think about it in
terms of memory. It's a huge uh memory
requirement for storing all of that. Uh,
so that's unfeasibly large, but it will
still like work pretty well for for
simple things. And then uh the other
problem um is that most sentences maybe
not most but like a lot of sentences
might be unique. Uh so if there's
something that never happened in your
training copus so if you never saw this
like very long text let's say that
instead of the grass is I give you a 100
lines um of of like code and I ask you
what's the next word maybe you never saw
these 100 lines of code at training time
and then your your predictor will have
no way to generalize because basically
count will be zero so we'll give a
probability of zero even though the
probability is actually a little bit
higher than zero that's like two
problems that you would have um with
this very simple kind of statistical uh
language model. Uh so the solution is
very simple just use neural network uh
neural networks. So if you I'm sure many
of you know about neural networks and
we're going to assume that you do but
basically you can just estimate well at
least approximate you can basically
approximate this prediction by using um
this uh this parametric estimator that
that neural networks are instead of this
nonparametric estimators that we talked
about here. Um great. So let's let's go
through what we what I'll call here
neural language models. So it's a
language model of a neural network which
is what everyone does. Um so the way
that this works at again at a very high
level is that you take a sentence for
example I saw a cat on a I will
basically split the sentence into
different tokens. I will associate so
these are all these words I will
associate all these tokens with
a word embedding. So like a vector
representation of um of that word. So
the way that you can think about it is
that uh imagine that this was in 2D. You
basically have um a plane and you
basically have all these points that are
that are on this plane where usually
like more similar words clustered with
one another. So you might you might have
like I saw cat and and things like this.
Uh it's just that instead of being 2D it
might be like much higher dimensional.
Um it might be like a vector space of
like 768 dimensional or something like
this. uh then you pass that to a neural
network. Uh so neural network the way to
think about it is just some some non
nonlinear aggregator of these vectors.
So it just takes it's just something
that takes all these uh vectors as
input. It does some merging and gives
you another vector. The important part
is that it's differentiable. So the way
that you do uh so you can actually back
propagate to that. That's like the the
most important. But for example, you
could use a very simple uh neural
network could just be uh an average of
this. You could literally just average
all these tokens together or the the
vectors associated with these tokens and
it gives you another another token here
which is intuitively it's the vector
representation of all this sentence I
saw a cat on.
Uh so yeah so again this is you could
take some average or you could just take
some like nonlinear uh nonlinear
aggregation like passing through a
neural network. Um then what you do is
that um this is the this vectoration is
in the wrong dimension because what you
want to is you want to be able to
predict the number of uh like which
which is the most likely word. Um so you
want to predict like the probability of
each word. So you want a representation
um that lives in uh this this
dimensional space that is the the number
of dimension is the number of tokens the
number of words that English that that
um that exist uh in your language for
example English. So what you will do
very simple way is that you can just
pass this to a linear uh layer. So you
can just multiply this by a matrix uh to
take this h rep uh this h representation
that lives in dimension and pass it to
your vocabulary size uh dimensions. So
let's say very concretely you have 768
dimension. Let's say that your
vocabulary might be like 20,000 uh words
that you might uh uh want to predict in
English and you will basically multiply
this this by a matrix of 768 by by
20,000 uh and then you will get a vector
out of it that is 20,000 dimensional.
Great. So once you have this you will
just pass it through a softmax. So soft
max is the usual trick to get a
categorical distribution. Um from from
any uh any vector. Um so this just uh
ensures that that basically you have
numbers that uh sum to one and are
between zero and one h and then you can
just um consider that as the probability
of the next word uh after I saw a cat on
earth. Um and here you have you have
here you are you basically have uh this
this prediction of the next word. Great.
And once you have the next word you can
just optimize the cross entropy loss. So
basically just try to optimize what the
real word is. Let's say that the real
word uh comes from here. You will
basically try to maximize a little bit
this one and minimize all the rest. And
then you just back propagate because
everything is differentiable and that
will basically tune all the weights that
you have in your in your neural network
including also these word embeddings. So
this representation for every word.
Okay, that was a very brief overview. Uh
but hopefully you get a sense of what a
neural language model is.
Okay. So now we talk about the talked
about the method. Let's talk about the
data um that goes into pre-training.
So the idea as I said before is to uh
basically use all of the clean internet.
So use as much data as possible and
everything that is clean on on internet.
Um why do I say all of clean internet is
because internet is actually the
majority of of internet is pretty kind
of dirty and not representative of what
what you want to ship um to to users or
what you want to uh what you want to
optimize your model on. Um so a very
practical type of pipeline. So
everything every every different like
lab and and different uh pre-training
groups have different ways of doing it.
But that's just to give you a broad
overview. You first download all of
internet. Um so uh usually people use in
the open source some uh common some some
crawlers uh that already downloaded
internet for them. Uh so basically for
example the common crawl is um is a
crawler that that already downloaded 250
billion pages. So that's one around like
more than one pabyte of data and they're
all in these uh walk uh files.
So basically download all of internet.
The the second thing and oh yeah and how
these look like so these files it's
basically just HTML. Um so you will see
that's pretty I mean it's hard to
understand. You see here some uh some
meta some keywords and here you will
find the text that says blah blah blah
blah or here paragraph one of the be one
of the best and most rewarding features
of the blah blah um no no or that. So,
it seems to be like an ad talking about
uh rewarding features and then it talks
about downloading free question and
answers. Um, anyways, it seems to be
pretty kind of an ad. Um, so anyways,
this is a random website that I took uh
from
from uh from Common Quil. So, as you
see, it's like kind of hard to pass and
uh probably this is not even something
that you really want to train on if it's
an app. Um, great. So, that's just an
example of what you have. Oh, my
computer stopped. Oh, like this. Great.
Second thing that you do, um, so as I
just saw, as you just saw, you have this
HTML. Um, so what you have to talk, what
you have to do is you have to extract
text out of it. Um, so it's actually
pretty challenging. there will be some
question of how do you deal like with
JavaScript or like boiler plate code or
like math that is not that is rendered
differently and things like this. Um so
you will need to extract text from HTML.
This is actually pretty computationally
uh expensive because at this point you
really have the name of the game is how
much data you can have. So you really
have a lot of data that you have to
clean and extract um from. So that's
actually pretty uh computationally
expensive. Then h you will do some
filtering. So, one uh one filter that
you we usually do that the open source
world does like pretty um pretty early
on is filtering for undesirable content
uh like uh PII data or like non-safe for
work data or anything that is harmful
like you will try to remove this. Um
then another very common filter that um
people usually do is dduplicating your
data. uh that the duplication could be
by document, it could be by line, it
could be by paragraph, it could be at
different levels. Uh but the idea is to
not train too much too many times on the
exact same data. Um for example, if you
train on on forums, let's say on on all
the data you have on on Wikipedia or
like Stack Overflow, you will always
have these like headers and footers that
are duplicated. And you definitely don't
want to train like a million times on
the exact same stack overflow header
because you don't learn much from it. So
you would basically be losing compute um
but to to try to learn the header
perfectly.
Okay. And then you will do some heristic
filtering. You might do some huristic
filtering. For example, you might remove
you might try to remove lowquality
documents. Um, low quality might be that
there are too many words. Like if it's
an extremely long document, it might be
suspicious. If it's a very short one,
like let's say there's only 10 words,
probably it's not worth training on. If
there's many kind of outlier tokens,
like tokens, so like words that really
like extremely rare, h it might um yeah,
it might be that this is just bad data.
So you'll do a lot of these huistic
based filtering. Um and then you might
also do some some model based filtering.
Uh so one one idea that I find pretty
neat that people have been doing is um
trying to uh basically do distribution
matching. So uh you find some
distribution that you find that you
think is high quality. Uh for example,
you might say Wikipedia is pretty high
quality. Um or you might say every page
that is referenced on Wikipedia is
likely to be high quality. Uh because
that means that someone went and
referenced that page. So that's a pretty
that's already a pretty big uh amount of
data. All those all the websites that
are linked by Wikipedia is pretty large.
Uh but it's still very little compared
to the amount of data that we need for
for pre-training. So what you might say
is I want to find more of that type of
data. Uh and the way you can do that is
that you can train a classifier uh that
uses some that takes some random data in
and says this is not a reference on
Wikipedia. and then the reference um uh
the pages that are referenced on on
Wikipedia and you try to predict
basically yes to this and no to the to
the uh to the former and then you once
you train that classifier you basically
have a classifier that essentially
predicts how likely your document is to
um how likely it is that your document
is referenced by Wikipedia and then you
can just do a filtering based on that.
uh so you can say if it's very likely I
keep if it's not likely at all I will
throw it away because it's likely it's
uh it's probably some bad bad data. So
this is some model based filtering and
you can do a lot of that uh and then you
can do some data mix uh data mix changes
for example you might like classify the
category of data whether it's like code
books entertainment like any any of
these domains and then you might want to
rewe different domains. So for example,
if you train a a coding model, you you
want to reweigh coding because probably
there's not enough code online. Um so
you want to say no, I even though I have
only that I only have like 5% of coding,
I want to bump it up to like 50%. Um and
the way
and the way to um to do this we waiting
like like you can uh usually do these
experiments at small scale. This is true
for any of these filtering. You might do
these experiments at small scale. Try to
understand um what is best and then you
will try to predict uh what to do at at
larger scale.
Great. Uh and at the end we'll talk
about that too. But uh once you did all
of this like pre-training data uh you
will also try to collect some higher
quality data. For example, some you
might say like Wikipedia is super high
quality or like everything on on like
archive might be like really high
quality. Uh so you will keep kind of
this second um uh this second
distribution of high quality data and
usually after training on this
pre-training data you will do what we
call mid training which is training on
this like high quality data. Uh the idea
being like well we don't have enough of
that data but we know it's high quality.
So we'll optimize uh we'll try to kind
of fine-tune or like optimize after
pre-training or continual pre-training
um uh our model on that high quality
data uh such that the the model learns
to to really be as good as possible.
Okay. So pre-training data um one one
paper that I would recommend reading is
this uh fine web and it's it's both a
paper and a blog post about fine web
data sets from hugging face um and they
talk a lot about uh what filtering
they've done um but this is just one
plot from their paper and here the
x-axis shows the amount of tokens
billion tokens that you train on this is
still pretty pretty small compared to uh
to the the scale of of pre-training data
that we talked about before which is
more than 10 trillion tokens and this is
the aggregated accuracy uh where it's
like basically your performance on on a
whole set of evals um and here what they
show is first uh this green line is when
you take they took 200 trillion tokens
um from um I believe common crawl and
then uh they so this is basically raw uh
data and then they applied a lot of
filters. So nons safe for work block
list they mostly went for English text
some simple document filtering uh for
example if it's too much repetition in
document they they they removed it or
it's the wrong length so that's this
first filtering went from 200 trillion
tokens to 36 trillion tokens and here we
see how um how well you perform when you
train on uh on 360 billion tokens from
those uh and here you see the
performance uh gain when you dduplicate
um data. So the way that they've done it
is they said uh essentially I don't want
to have text that is duplicated more
than 100 100 times. Um so that's
basically at a high level. So they
filter data they filtered by nearly half
from 36 trillion tokens to 20 trillion
tokens. And you see that tr training on
that really improves performance. Um,
again, that's because you're basically
uh not forcing your model to like learn
things that are uh that are duplicated
and like not not that useful and you
really focus on on new data. Um, so so
that that yeah, that worked pretty well
for them. And I mean 100 100 documents
or like 100 documents that are that are
duplicated is still quite a lot, but but
usually you can have a huge clusters of
like a 100,000 duplicates. So that those
are the ones that that they wanted to
filter out. Um and here you see some
additional filtering. So for example,
they removed I believe JavaScript. They
removed like LAR, ipsum text and things
like this. So that removed a little bit
uh again a little bit more of data and
you see that performs better and then
some additional I believe model based
filtering that performed even better.
Great. So that's pre-training data and
then is there's mid training. Um so as I
said before the idea of mid training is
basically continuing your pre-training
uh to adapt your model to have some
desired properties or to basically adapt
your model on some higher quality data.
Uh so usually you do it on basically
less than 10% of what you you did for
pre-training. Um so less than than the
trillion token
um so you might for example change the
data mix in your data. So you might say,
I want to have a lot of coding data um
at the end or I want to be more
scientific and have like a model that is
really good at scientific um yeah at sc
yeah yeah basically science questions uh
or you might want to optimize more
multilingual data. Let's say that uh
let's say that you have you know that
data is usually a lot of the data that
you we have access to is more English
but this is not representative of uh the
languages that people uh usually speak.
So you might say, okay, I'm going to
upate um some other languages that are
that we usually are less represented in
our data sets just to make sure that
it's basically representative of how
many people speak that language.
Um some other type of of uh um things we
do during mid training or that we might
want to do uh is that you usually want
to increase context length. Um so in
many of these models you usually hear uh
this idea of like how much how much data
sorry how much context can the model see
um and when you do pre-training you
don't want to train on very large
context lengths u because uh that's much
more computationally intensive but you
do want the model to be able to
understand let's say like a 100 120
tokens that came before uh your
question. Um so usually what you do
during mid training is that you will
bump up this this context uh context
length. So you will do some extension of
uh context length during mid training.
Um for for DeepC V3 they went from four
uh from 4,000 uh contexts um during
pre-training to 128 uh during mid
training and I think many other open
source projects did that. Um other type
of data you might want to add is some
some formatting on instruction
following. Um, so you might want to
already teach your model to like answer
questions when you uh ask a question uh
or to write in a very specific kind of
chatty way. Um, and some high quality
data. uh if you have some high quality
data, you might keep it for the end and
be like, okay, once I f like first I
want to learn how to kind of like speak
uh grammatically correctly. Um and then
I want to actually learn the real uh
kind of meat of uh of um the text that
you have in your data. Uh and you might
have some reasoning data about like
teaching the model how to think. Um
which I believe is is what Kimmy did. Um
and yes many other things. Great. Uh so
pre-training and mid training let's just
do a recap.
Um one is is that really this data doing
pre-training training is a is a really a
huge part of training LMS. I would even
say that it's basically the key for
training LLMs. Um and there's a lot of
research that uh has already been done
and a lot more to be done. uh for
example how do you process well and
efficiently I mean these are huge scales
of data are we talking about whether to
use synthetic data and whether to use
basically models to like uh generate
more data how much multimodal data to
put in how to balance your domains and
all of that um and there's a lot of
secrecy uh so most companies um are not
talking uh about what they do even the
companies that actually do open source
models don't usually talk that much
about the data that they collected uh
first because it's the most important
thing. Uh so there's competitive
dynamics like they don't want to tell
you um what they've been training on
because that would be easier to
replicate. Um and then there's some some
companies might be scared about
copyright liability if they train on
data that they shouldn't have trained
on.
Um so here are a few common academic
data sets. C4 which is uh yeah C4 the
pile map fine web I just wrote a few. Um
so fin web is the one we talked about
before 15 trillion tokens and this is uh
this is the pal uh the composition of
the pal uh and you see that in the pal
there's a lot of archive and like pubmed
and a high quality data um and you will
have also a good amount of like code and
things like this
great um so just to give you a scale of
these data as I said lama 2 was trained
around like two trillion tokens lama
around 15 lma 4 between 20 and and 40
children tokens. So every new generation
tries to train on more data um and do
all does also some some better
filtering.
Okay. So that was about a pre-training
uh data aspect. Now let's talk about the
compute. Um so empirically like one
thing that is super important is that
empirically for any type of data and
model the most important as I said
before is uh how much compute uh you
basically spend on on data uh sorry on
training. Um so by how much compute I
mean both kind of how much data do you
put in the model and the size of of the
model because if the size if the model
is bigger you need to spend more
compute. Um
and what is very nice is that you can
actually predict pretty well the
performance at least during pre-training
you can predict pretty well the
performance that you will achieve uh if
you just pour more compute uh into your
run. So if you just train for longer um
or train bigger models you can predict
pretty well how how well they will
perform. So here the way to interpret uh
um this this plot is that on the x-axis
you see the amount of compute um that
you you have in your run. This is in log
scale and here you have your test loss
also in log scale. And all these blue
lines are basically different runs. Um,
and then you take the minimum achieved
uh for all of these runs and you can you
can like t like link all of them
together and it it gives you something
that looks pretty sim pretty close to a
line and then you can just fit the line
uh to to this uh to this cover um to
discover of the ideal
compute and test loss. And now you can
use this line to predict how well can
you perform if you train on 10 times
more data. Oh sorry on 10 with 10 times
more compute or 100 times more compute.
Um so what is very nice is what I wrote
here is that you can now do research at
very low scales and then predict how
well it will perform at like higher
scales. So this is what we call a
scaling loss which has uh which one is
very surprising. there's really no uh
good reason for this to happen or at
least
yeah it could have been differently. Um
there are some theories for for why that
happened. Um and and two it's it's uh I
mean it's it's really very uh it's very
nice when you do research because now it
means you can work at this small scale
and has uh really been great for the
field. Okay. Okay, so scaling laws. What
is nice as I said is that now you can
tune things at lower scale. For example,
if you have um if I ask you a question
and I gave you 10,000 GPUs,
how like I asked you how do you how
should you be using these 10,000 GPUs?
How should you be training that model?
Like historically what you might have
done is you might like tune a high
parameters for different models. So you
might say, okay, I'm going to have 20
different runs or 30 different runs and
I'm going to pick the best and that's
the one that I'm going to um ship. But
as a result, uh each of them will only
be trained on like 13th of the compute
that you had access to. The new pipeline
is that now you can find scaling
recipes. So you can find like recipes
that tell you how to change like the
learning rate with with different scales
and things like this. Um then you can
tune hyper parameters at small scale for
a very short amount of time uh and for
very like you can do many many
iterations and then you can plot the
scaling law extrapolate how well you
will be performing at larger scale and
then train one huge model at the end
where you use way more of the compute
that you have access to. So maybe like
90% of your compute goes for the full
run rather than like 130th of what you
had before.
So yeah this is really a blessing.
Okay. So for example very concretely
should you use an architecture that is a
transformer or an LSTM you see that um
uh you see that transformers this is the
scaling law for transformers and here
you see LSTMs you see that transformers
have a better constant. So that means
that they are always lower than uh than
LSTMs and they also have a better
scaling rate. You see here that LSTM
seems to be plateauing a little bit. So
that tells you both that at any scale
transformers is better but also the
larger the scale the better the
transformer becomes. Um which is why
most people like people gave up on
essentially LSTMs
as an architecture. Um but what's
interesting is it could have been the it
could also just be that the constant is
better for one of the architectures but
the scaling rate is better for the other
one. And in that case, you definitely
want to always go with the scaling rate,
not the constant because who cares how
well it performs at very small scale.
The real question is what what if it's
like two like 200 times larger? Uh how
does it perform there? And that's why
the scaling rate is what matters. Um
great. So um one very famous paper about
scaling laws is chinchilla that tries to
explain how tries to show what is the
optimal way of allocating training
resources between size the size of the
the model and the data because both of
these things are about compute and as we
said the more compute the better but you
can either there are two ways of of
spending compute either you train for
longer or you train larger models um so
so they have these results I'm going to
skip a little bit but you can basically
predict
the the optimal the optimal resource
allocation and they found that for every
parameter you should be using around 20
tokens. So that's kind of this optimal
uh this optimal uh resource allocation.
Uh one thing to note you will hear often
about chinchilla but chinchilla is only
an optimization of training resources.
It doesn't consider inference costs. So
they will only ask themselves like they
only ask what is uh the best way to
achieve a certain training loss um like
how much like where should I be where
should I be putting the compute but it
doesn't take into account that if you
have larger models sorry if you have
larger models at inference time it will
actually cost more um so for example if
if I have I mean let's say for example
CH like for open for GPT the larger the
model, the more you will spend per user.
So, uh you might be better off using
actually training for longer um and and
training a smaller model e even if it
means that you need to spend more uh
compute to achieve the same performance
because at inference time it will cost
less. Um anyway, so that's uh that's the
chinchilla paper and then I want to talk
a little bit about the bitter lesson. um
from from Sutton. So, so basically the
bit of lesson uh I would really
recommend reading uh this uh this blog
post from Richard Sudden uh which is um
really the the the the big uh researcher
of of reinforcement learning and he
wrote that blog post that essentially
tries to says the only thing that
matters in the long run is is about
leveraging compute and the reason why is
because uh we see imply that the larger
like the more comput you put in the
models um the the more improvements you
get out of it. So basically uh more
compute equals better performance and we
also know from like Mo's law and like
some um derivative uh laws uh that we
will always have more compute or at
least that's kind of the hope we will
always have more compute every year. And
if you put these two things together,
more compute equals better performance
and you will always have more compute.
Um then the the the natural things that
come out of it is that it's all about
leveraging computation. There's no
reason for trying to optimize things at
your current uh level of compute because
next year you will have more and that
will just perform better. So what
matters is to have methods that will
scale up really well. Um so that's kind
of the uh the TLDDL uh for the beta
lesson which is uh really has has driven
a lot of of how the community has been
thinking in the last like I would say
three four years.
Uh so yeah so the the summary is don't
spend time over complicating things do
the simple thing uh and make sure that
it scales because what matters again
it's not kind of tuning this this
constant performance is really uh making
sure that you can scale it up
um great so for training a sort of model
that's um
this is a slide that I I wrote um maybe
two years ago uh or one or two years ago
for training lath 3 400B which at the
time was the largest open- source model
and I just tried to predict like how
much that would cost. So in terms of
data I was trained on 15.6 trillion
tokens uh 405 billion parameters. Uh and
you see here that uses around 40 tokens
per parameter. Um so that's pretty kind
of train computes optimal by chili
standards. Uh in terms of flops,
it uses uh 3.8 uh E25 uh flops. Um so
there's an executive order that says
that you need to uh to basically uh you
need to be more careful when you when
you uh open source models or when you
when you train models that are more than
uh one E 26 flops. So this is around two
times less than executive order. um
in terms of flops, in terms of compute,
they use 16,000 H100s.
Um and if you do the computation, in
terms of time, it probably takes uh
around 70 days of uh of training uh to
train this model. And in terms of cost,
my rough estimate is that uh it would
cost around like 52 uh million dollars
for training this. So between 50 and
like 80 million uh depending on on how
much yeah how much you consider that
they spend per compute given their own
clusters. Um and in terms of like carbon
emitted for training this uh this is
around just for training that one model
maybe 2,000 return tickets um from JFK
to London. So from New York to London.
Um so that's that's quite a lot. Uh it's
still neglectable compared to um to
uh I mean how many flights there are per
year per year and things like this. But
if you think that every every generation
is going to be like maybe 10 times more
compute than the previous generation,
you could see how in like two three four
generations uh that will become a real
issue in terms of carbon emitted. Um
in terms of next model as I said it's
around basically every generation you
can think about it as like 10 times more
flops uh that go into training the
models. Great. Um okay so pre-training
summary the idea is about predicting the
next word on internet uh data around 10
trillion uh words go into training these
models right now. Um in terms of time it
takes months in terms of compute um more
than $10 million. The bottl neck is data
and computation. Um and some examples
might be DC v4 DC v3 and lama lama 4.
Okay. So now we talked about
pre-training. Let's talk about post
training. Again I'll talk about the
method, the data and compute. So uh why
do you want to do post training? Um well
language modeling. So what we do during
pre-training is really not about
assisting users and about helping users.
Um so language modeling is not what you
want. And what I mean by that is that if
you just take GP3 and you ask you prompt
it with explain the moon landing to a
six-year-old in a few sentences, what it
will do is that it has been trained on
on basically a large part of internet.
So it will say well that reminds me of
maybe large lists of question that
people might ask. So instead of
answering the question, it might just
predict what is the next type of what is
a similar type of question that people
might ask. So actually what GBD3 answers
to you is explain the theory of gravity
to a six-year-old. Explain a theory of
of relativity to blah blah. So this is
uh this really shows you that like these
models are really not optimized for
predicting what you want. This is just
about language modeling predicting the
next word. Um so the idea of kind of
classic post training uh also called
instruction following or alignment is
about steering the model to be useful on
real world tasks. Uh so if I ask explain
the moon landing to a six-year-old in a
few sentences the same as before I want
chat GPT or any model to give me a real
answer and the way that we basically do
that is to maximize um the preferences
of humans. So maximize answer
preferences of humans. Um in terms of
data probably around like between 5,000
and 500,000 problems. So much much
smaller scale than pre-training. Uh the
idea is that uh first you do first you
try to basically learn everything in the
world and then you try to optimize on
very specific domains which is in this
case kind of just like instruction
following and answering questions uh
with very few data points because the
model already knows everything. So it
just needs to learn how to basically how
to act or how to interact with the um
with the human and this is really what
made ch
what it is. Um so since 2022 that's
really when when posting became
important
and then so that's that's the overview
of this like third stage that I told you
about which is the classic posting. And
then there's the second stage um which
is about teaching the model to reason.
So that only happens in some models. Um
for example, Kimmy and R1
and the the idea is to optimize simply
answering the right question. Um is
answering correctly the good the
question. So you will see some for
example in 01 it says things like
thought for 24 seconds. Uh so reasoning
is about how do you optimize for that?
The data that usually optimize for is
basically any hard task with verifiable
answers. So things like math
competitions or like coding test cases
um and you try to optimize for that. So
this really became important since 01 in
2024. Um and uh yeah this is about this
new paradigm of reasoning.
uh and I believe no uh from open will
also come and and tell you um about
reasoning but at a at a very high level
the idea is that what we had before was
was train time compute. So we talked we
I mentioned to you uh scaling laws which
shows that the more compute you pour in
the in the run during training the
better your performance is and one
reason it gave you is test time compute.
So after training, you can also pull
more compute in your model to get better
performance. And that's kind of like fit
like humans. If you make me answer a
question in in a second, I will probably
write a less thoughtful and less and
less correct answer than if I you gave
me like a week to answer the question.
So the goal was test time scaling.
Um
let me put a little bit more light.
Great. uh so post training methods I
will talk about SFT and and
reinforcement learning
so uh the task is alignment uh let's say
that you want to optimize just as an
example let's say that we want to
optimize uh the LM to follow user
instructions or some like designer's
desires um so this is the example from
before which is like answering questions
or maybe you want the model to like uh
never answer specific type of questions
for example if I ask write a tweet
describing how X uh this like X people
are evil. Uh you might want your model
not to answer that question.
So kind of the what I told you before is
I didn't question of of post training in
general is that um
you actually know what you want to
provide to these models. Um you do know
the type of answers that you want to
give uh sorry to give to humans. you
want do know the type of answers that
you want to give to humans and what you
want your model to like follow. Uh but
that behavior like these answers are
scarce and expensive. So it's pretty
expensive and and and slow to also
collect that type of data. Uh but you
you could just go and and try to ask
humans what are all the correct answers
to every question that you you might
want to ask. Um so the idea is that you
know what data you you um you know what
data you you know what you want your
model to to output uh but it's expensive
to collect that data. Um with
pre-training is is something where it's
very easy to collect that data. You just
take all of internet essentially but
it's not really what you want as we
said. Um so the idea is that instead
given that one is scalable but it's not
what you want and the other one is not
scalable is what you want. What you can
do is that you will basically take the
pre-trained model um that already
learned about like grammar and and and
different languages and you will just
fine-tune it uh or like do some like
some small optimization with data with
the little amount of data that uh that
is in the format that you want and this
is what we call post training. Okay, so
there are two methods. The first one is
supervised finetuning. Uh so the idea is
again just to fine-tune the LM with uh
with language modeling. So the exact
same method as before but you do it on
desired answers. Um so instead of just
predicting the next word you predict the
next word on answers that are the
answers that you would want to give to
humans. Uh so this language modeling it
means that it's again next word
prediction and desired answers is why we
say supervised fine tuning. Um and so
where the s comes from is because you
you assume that you have access to kind
of the correct answer. um which is why
it's supervised. So how can we collect
that data? There are many different
ways. One is just to ask humans
um and uh this this was kind of the key
from GPT3 to GPT the initial GPT model.
Uh and here are some examples from from
open assistant that that did that in the
uh in the open source where you have a
question and then you have answers that
are written by humans. Um you can also
do it differently not you can also yeah
one problem basically with free human
data is that it's slow to collect and
it's expensive. Um so one idea that you
might want to do is to use an LLM to
scale data collection. Um so uh this is
what we did for Alpaca for example in uh
in early 2023 where we basically said
well we don't have the money or we don't
have the we don't have the luxury of of
uh having humans that provide our senses
but what we can do is that we can use
the best model for from open air at the
time to predict the right answer and we
can basically try to do supervised fine
tuning with the answer that is given by
the open air models. Uh so we did that
on 52,000
um uh answers and we basically these are
some examples and uh and that kind of
yeah that was one of the first uh or
probably the first uh instruction
following uh rep LLM uh in the open
source. Um so that really saw it as kind
of a trying to replicate CH GPT. Um and
and now uh this synthetic data
generation is is a whole field on its
own. Um because uh yeah the idea is that
now actually some of these models are
just better than the humans. Uh so it's
not only that like humans are slow and
as it's not only that like human data
collection is slow and expensive. It
might just be that it's like low lower
um quality. Um so yeah okay so let's
talk about um uh yeah so for SAT there
there's there's another another way of
doing it so we talked about uh two ways
right now we talked about humans we
talked about LM that just provide an
answer uh but the problem is that if you
want to do LM provides if you want an LM
to provide an answer you kind of assume
that you have access to an LM that is
smaller than the LM that you're training
um and that That was uh indeed the case
when we were training alpaca. But this
is not the case if you're for example in
um in the the best closed labs which are
training kind of the frontier models or
even if you're in the input open source
and you're training trying to uh uh
train the best open source models might
not have access to or be able to uh um
uh distill like closed closed models. Uh
so what did DeepSseek R1 do? Um because
they were training this like first it's
like top top open source model. Uh the
idea is that you can use uh rejection
sampling based on verifiers. So what I
mean by that is that you can just use an
LLM uh to provide many different answers
um to a question and then you only keep
the answer if it passes some if it's
correct in some sense. So if it passes
some like test case or some verification
um or if it's preferred over other
answers. So the idea again is well you
don't have an ideal LLM that you uh that
you can generate data from and then and
then um train do SFT to predict that
data. What you can do is if you have
access to verifiers or ways of like
comparing different samples is you can
uh roll out many samples then decide
which one is is better based on your
verifier and then do SFT on the sample
that is given by the verifier. Um so
that's exactly what DeepS R1 did uh for
the first stage of of reinforcement
learning. Um so or sorry for the first
stage of of SFT.
Great.
Um, so what do we learn from JSFT? What
are the type of things that we can
learn? Well, we already talked about it.
We can learn instruction following
following instructions. Uh, you can
learn desired formatting or style like
be more chatty or like use like emojis
or things like this. You can use tool
use. So I would recommend reading if
you're interested in that the Kim 2
paper, the XLAN paper that tell that
basically uses SF at scale to learn how
to use tools. Um, you can uh learn some
early reasoning. So how to think before
answering which is exactly what we just
talked about with Deepseek R1 where they
use this rejection sampling algorithm.
Um and honestly you can kind of learn
anything where you have good inputs and
output bests.
Um so SFT can either be seen as a final
stage for training a final model or as a
preparation for the next stage which is
the reinforcement learning stage. Um so
you don't want to basically given that
this works pretty well you might want to
do that first before doing the next
stage um to to accelerate the next stage
as we will see. Uh so SFT pipelines can
become pretty complex. I'm not going to
talk through this one in in in detail
but I just want to give you a sense of
how complicated it can be. Uh this is
about Kimmy K2. Uh so I would recommend
reading that paper and how they use SFT
for training uh for tool use. Uh so
basically teaching the model to use
tools. Um and and what they did is
pretty complicated with some LM that
simulates users simulates tools and then
do this this like rejection sampling
that we talked about before. Uh and uh
yeah so the idea is that they collected
a lot of tools. Um they simulated a lot
of synthetic tools that tell you like
how how the tool should be called and
then they basically have an agent that
uh interacts with an LLM that simulates
user and another LLM that simulates tool
calls. Uh because otherwise like tool
calls um you might not have access to
enough different tools uh to to really
simulate like all tools that might be
that might be uh called by the the
model. And then you basically do some
rejection sampling uh based on these
rollouts that were generated with these
three LMs that interact with one
another. The the agent LM, the user LM,
and the tool simulating LM. Um anyways,
all this to say that these things can
become pretty complex but still work
pretty well. Okay. Uh so scalable data
for SFT, how much data do you need? um
SFT what is nice is that you actually
don't need that much data uh for
learning simple things like style and
instruction following maybe 10,000 is
enough. Uh so this is uh from a paper a
lema paper in 2023 that basically shows
that already with 2,000 examples you
kind of learn the style and um
instruction following uh capabilities
that you want. If you want to train like
more complicated things like tool use
and and reasoning um you you might want
to increase that. I believe R1 used
800,000
uh samples which is a good amount but
basically less less than a million at
least. Um so yeah the the idea is that
you don't need to train on much data for
SFT if the model already like learned
that. Um so the intuition I usually like
my intuition for these type of things or
my mental model is that everything that
is already you learned really well
during pre-training um but you just want
to surface during post training things
like how to write in bullet points or
like how to use emojis
um in your model. This is more about
like specializing your model to one
particular like type of user uh that it
has already modeled during pre-training.
Then for that you don't need that much
data. If it's for things that are that
it has never seen during pre-training or
very little then you need much more
data.
Okay. Um so that brings us to uh
reinforcement learning. So the second uh
method which is RL uh so in
reinforcement learning um the the the
idea yeah the idea that we try the
problem that we try to solve with
reinforcement learning is that SFT is
about behavior cloning of humans or of
outputs as we saw could be from LLMs too
but it's about behavior cloning it's
about copying the behavior of different
outputs and this has many issues one is
that it's kind of bound by human
abilities or bound by the abilities of
the LMS that you're copying Um but but
humans even if you're actually
collecting human data they might not
prefer the things that they are
generating. Um so even though they might
not write like better answers not might
be able to write might not be able to
write better answers uh they can still
say like which one they prefer. Um so
yeah the idea is that you will always be
bound by human abilities. Uh the second
thing is that you will actually teach
hallucination. Um, and this is a pretty
yeah that's a a pretty interesting
behavior is that even if you're cloning
correct answers or correct behavior, you
might actually be teaching the model to
hallucinate if that model did not know
that that answer was correct. So what do
I mean by that? Imagine that I ask a
question to write some some
introduction. Um uh yeah this is some
text and basically I ask to provide some
references. Um if it provides a
reference sorry if if the answer
provides a reference that the model does
not know about. Basically what you're
teaching the model is you're teaching
the model provide something that seems
like a plausible reference even though
that reference even if that reference
was not in your pre-training corpus. So
even if you don't know if that exists
still like generate that. Um so you're
basically teaching the model to like
make up plausibly sounding references.
Um so yeah so hallucination that's one
issue. Uh and a third thing is that um
collecting ideal answers can be pretty
expensive.
Um so the idea or like one solution is
to instead of doing behavior cloning or
SFT you can do reinforcement learning.
So instead of cloning the behavior you
can maximize that behavior.
So I would really recommend reading the
Deepseek R1 paper and the Kimik K2
papers that are uh some of the best
papers out there in the open source. Um
and the key here is the key in
reinforcement learning is to to decide
like what are you maximizing? Uh what is
the reward that you're maximizing? Um
there are different things for example
that uh that that uh R1 has been
optimizing for. One might be rulebased
rewards things like string matches. Uh
let's say that you have close-ended
question and answering. You might just
uh say your answer is correct if the
answer is exactly X. Um or you could
have some test cases uh for coding. So
that's rule-based rewards. You can have
reward models that were trained to
predict human preferences. Um so we will
talk a little bit about that. But you
can basically uh train a classifier to
predict whether something is good or bad
as predicted by a human and then like
optimize against that. Or you might
optimize against an LM as a judge. So
using an LM like let's say use the best
possible LM and you just say like what
is that answer correct or not. Um so
here uh yeah you see this particular
case which says write a Python code blah
blah blah and then the model generates
different answers and here given that
you say let's write a Python code you
might have rulebased verification it
says well this is not code here this is
the answer here's a joke about frogs
this is not code I asked for Python code
so is it Python or not if it's not
Python uh then it's also wrong and then
it might check like if you pass some
test cases is um and it will only keep
the ones that are passing. So the idea
is to optimize the things that are
currently passing. So you just say to
the model do more of the thing that uh I
gave you a correct reward for or
positive reward for.
Um
great. So
yeah, as I said before, I would
recommend uh reading the DeepS R1 paper.
Uh but basically they use uh for for
reasoning pro what they call reasoning
prompts so like math questions, coding
questions and some logical reasoning
they use these rulebased verifiers that
we just talked about. Um and then for
general prompts like translation factual
question answering and uh and and
writing requests things that are more
like long form uh text uh they basically
use a reward model that was trained to
predict human preferences and they try
to optimize that. Uh so they what they
do is that they start with this SFT
checkpoint. So they use a model they
they do some SFT like this. The model is
already pretty good at generating things
that um that are often correct and then
you just do this reinforcement learning
pipeline where you try to optimize the
number of times that your verifier says
you're correct.
So in terms of algorithm um the the most
common algorithm in the open source is
GRPO from Deepseek R1. Uh and the idea
is actually pretty simple uh is that you
take uh a policy model. So you take your
your LLM that was usually trained from
um uh there's usually SFT uh model. Uh
you give you ask it to answer multiple
times um to provide multiple outputs to
your question. And then let's skip that
part for now. You basically have a
reward model or verifier that tells you
that gives a reward that tells you like
yes it was correct, no it was wrong by
how much and all of this. you get a
reward for each and then you basically
uh compute yeah do some some uh group
computation uh to to get um your
advantage your advantage advantages. The
way to just think about is if you do
some uh normalization um just so that
you know if uh which one is very good
and which one is very bad. you basically
renormalize
um all of these rewards and then you ask
your you basically back propagate to
tell your policy like do more of the
thing that was good uh and then usually
the the one we skipped here is this
reference model you usually have a KL
divergence which means that you ask uh
the policy model during training you say
don't move too far uh from outputs from
my base model um and this is really just
a hack because you're basically saying
reinforcement learning can get you in
places that are usually don't that are
usually not ideal
for example, the hacks that we talked
about. So that's like one way of just
saying don't go too far. Optimize as
well as you can, but uh but with with
certain limits of of how far you can go.
Yeah. And so this is not super
important, but basically if you know a
little bit of reinforcement learning,
Deepseek R1 optimizes GRPO, which is
really uh which really just uses the
Monteolo estimate for computing the
advantage. uh and Kimik K 1.5 and Kimik
K2 use a similar loss.
Um okay so one thing I want to emphasize
is that uh in reinforcement learning
infra is really key is really really
important. Um and the reason why is
because as you saw if you use this GPO
algorithm uh sampling is a key ball
because for every uh for every input uh
or every question you have to sample
multiple outputs for each of these
problems. Um and especially for agents
given that this is a agent class this
becomes even worse because uh you you
might have very long agentic rollouts
and you basically don't want to block
all your compute. um all your training
compute on these very long agentic
rollouts that are being rolled out. So
uh Kimmy did a lot of optimization and I
would again recommend reading their
papers. Uh for example for long rollouts
Kimmy decided to pause uh these long
rollouts. So if it's more than a certain
than a certain amount of time they will
basically pause the roll out and then
we'll say okay this is not worth it. We
will do some we will optimize our
weights and then we will resume the roll
out the next step. Um, and then another
issue with agents is that the
environment feedback can be slow. So if
you have an agent that really interacts
with the world and calls a lot of APIs
and things like this, um, like maybe
you're not even you're not even using
your GPUs at all because maybe you're
not even like doing rollouts. Maybe
you're just waiting for the environment
response response. Uh so the way that
Kimmy bypasses that is by using really a
lot of concurrent rollouts like this
when when a certain rollout is waiting
on environment response you can work on
something else. Um and dedicated
services that microservices that can
really like spin up and and and scale.
Um and the way that they've that Kimmy
did it is that for every part they have
a train engine. Um then they have a
checkpoint engine that broadcasts all
the weights uh to all the other uh all
the other uh pods and then they have an
inference engine uh that really does
this this sampling and what is important
is everything is collocated all the
engines are collocated on the same pod
uh to avoid like communication overhead.
Um so anyways all this to say that
there's a lot of optimiz optimization uh
on the infraite and like uh infra is
really key here. So the communication
for them less takes less than 30 seconds
uh for communicating the the weights and
everything is again working on the same
part.
Okay. So let's talk about reinforcement
learning from human feedback which uh
right now we talked about reinforcement
learning when you basically for
reasoning when you have usually ground
truth verifiers. The reinforcement
learning for from human feedback LHF is
um is this uh uh this notion of
reinforcement learning when you don't
have ground truth. This is really what
made GPT uh work um in 2022. Uh so the
idea is instead of SFT where you clone
the behavior of humans you you want to
maximize their their preferences. Um as
I said this is what made GPT and the
pipeline is the following. Um this is
how the original algorithm for JGPT
worked. You have an instruction that
goes to a model like a question that
goes to model. You ask the model to
provide two answers. Um and usually the
model is already pretty good. It's an
SFT model. Uh and then you ask some
labelers to select which of the two was
better. So you ask some humans, hey,
which one of the two was better? And
then you uh you basically um predict you
you basically maximize the number of
times that you will generate the thing
or you will optimize more you will tell
your model to predict more of this this
thing that was correct. Um so there are
different algorithms I'm not going to go
through them. Uh PO and DPO are two of
them for for doing that. Uh but
basically this is just reinforcement
learning uh where where your reward is
actually given by a reward model that
was trained to classify human
preferences.
Um and here you see the these are pretty
old results uh by now but uh here you
see um for learning to summarize how a
pre-trained model performs for
summarization SFT performs better. This
is kind of like human reference summary.
So how well you compared to humans and
uh so SFD really improved compared to
pre-training but then you see PO so this
reinforcement learning made you perform
even better and this is kind of the the
order of things where it's like
pre-training is good SAT is better and
then and is even better um and same
thing here and those are like this is
alpaca farm which is a paper we did for
for kind of optimizing human preferences
and you see that here that the two
algorithms here those two are two RL
algorithms
work similarly and and they work better
in SFT and they work better in the
retraining model.
Okay. Um human data. So uh as I said
human would come from sorry data comes
from humans. This is very expensive uh
or at least very uh it takes a long time
to do and pretty expensive too. You have
to write extremely detailed rubrics to
tell to tell humans what is even
considered as a good answer, what is
considered as a bad answer. Um it's
actually pretty uh yeah a lot of work
that goes into collecting data is is
hard. Collecting data is hard. Um
challenges with human data as I just
said it's slow and expensive. Uh second
it's like it's actually hard for really
focusing on the content of the answers.
Most humans when you ask them what is
good and what is bad h they will usually
kind of focus on the form or like the
style things like lengths um and this is
usually not what you want to optimize
for in your in your LLM. Um also
depending on who you ask the the
distribution of of annotators you will
really get different behaviors uh like
different like particle views um and uh
yeah different views on on many things.
So you have to be pretty pretty mindful
about that. Um there's also crowd
sourcing ethics um uh involved here uh
like who who are you asking to label
your data. Um and yeah so there's a lot
of challenges with with human data.
Okay. Uh so one way to reduce this this
dependency on human data is exactly what
uh what I told you about before with SFT
is that you can ask an LLM to replace
humans to provide preferences. And this
is a paper again this alpaca paper that
we wrote uh two years ago um which shows
on the x- axis the amount of dollars
that you need to spend um for collecting
data on the y-axis you see uh the
agreement with humans um and and you see
that actually humans I believe are in
blue so here so this is around $300 per
1,000 examples to that we had to pay uh
uh humans
And you see that the agreement between
different humans is around 66%. Well,
for for LMS, we could go uh we could
divide by 10 or even by 30 the amount of
money that we spent. Um and that was two
years ago. Right now, it would be way
way less than that and we actually
performed already better than humans on
predicting uh the correct human answer.
So, it works surprisingly well. So, you
can you can always kind of use this
trick of using LMS instead of humans.
But again, uh this is harder to do when
you're at the the frontier and you don't
have a better LM.
Um
okay. And then evaluation.
So um there's I'll I'll talk really
briefly about that, but there's uh
basically two types of evaluation.
Close-ended evaluation and open-ended
evaluation. Um and uh one thing to
notice really evaluation is the key is
really the key. it is the most important
thing um or one of the most important
things in in machine learning in general
and AI uh and the reason why is for
three reason first
uh what it does is that it it it's key
to identify improvements uh to know to
quantify progress that you're making uh
and to to say whether you're actually
yeah to say whether you're making
progress and and what to change what
high parameters to select and things
like this. Um the second thing that's
really important for is that it will uh
allow you to select which model. So if I
have which model to use for your
application, if I have a specific
application in mind, I will have all
these different models to train for to
to use um yeah to choose from and I
would need to know like which one to to
go after or to choose. And finally um
it's very important to know evaluation
is really important to know whether uh
your model is ready to be put in
production like even though your model
might be the best current model like is
it good enough to uh for your
application this is very important for
practical use cases you really need to
have good evaluations um of your lives.
So close-ended evaluation um the idea is
that if you can turn your problem into
something where you have a few possible
answers then you can easily auto
automatically verify whether your answer
is correct. Uh for example, if you have
a if you turn your email into a question
answering evaluation, um then you can
simply ask an LM to provide an an answer
that is the answer like A, B or C and
you simply like look at what the right
answer was and then you just consider
like your accuracy. So this is for
example what the MMLU Eval did. Um so
there's still many issues. There's still
challenges with closed end evaluation.
uh one it's sensitive to prompting like
different ways that you prompt your
model will provide different answers. Um
two it might have like train test
contamination
uh so if your model was like trained on
on the the eval because right now for
example MLU is all all over internet
like maybe your models was like trained
on that it will see much better than
what it actually is. Um so this is about
closed-ended evaluation. uh I won't
really want to focus on open-end
evaluation because despite uh these
challenges closed end evaluation is much
easier than open-end evaluation. Um the
question for open-end evaluation is how
do we event evaluate something like CHP
or like an LLM. Um so CHPT or all these
these instruction following models uh
they can be applied on so many different
things. uh so they you can be applying
it for for like coding for for chatting
for summarization for many things. So
you really want to have an an eva that
kind of covers all these use cases. Uh
the second thing is that it's open-ended
task. So what I mean by that is that you
have very like long answers. Um and as a
result you can't do this this uh this uh
accuracy based evaluation where you just
check uh whether the answer is verbatim
like the correct answer. Um so that
makes it hard. Uh so you cannot do this
uh um the string matching to know
whether you're correct. Uh so one idea
that you you might have for closing in
evaluation is that you can simply ask
humans uh to tell you whether the answer
um like which answer is preferred. So
you might show two answers to a human
and just ask which of the two two is
better.
Uh so this is what chatbot arena by lmis
did where you basically ask humans to
blindly interact with two chatbot and
kind of rate which one is better. Uh so
that's one way of doing that of
basically dealing with this challenge
where when you ask open-ended uh tasks
with like long where there's not a
single answer and the answers are
usually really long. Uh it's easier yeah
it's much easier to just ask humans to
kind of rank things than uh than to
compare to a gold answer because there's
no gold answer.
Uh the problem with this is that using
uh using humans is again kind of costly
and and and expensive sorry expensive
and and slow. So just as before uh what
you can do is you can use an LLM instead
of a human. This is what we did with
alpaka eval two years ago and and and
many others followed. Um and uh the the
idea here the steps is that for each
instruction for each question you might
ask a baseline that could be a human or
model to provide an answer and the model
that you try to evaluate to provide an
answer. Um and then you will just ask
another LM which of the two answers is
better. Um so and and then you will just
kind of look at the number of times that
your answer is better than the baseline.
Um and you can get what we call a win
rate which is probability of of winning.
Um so alaka eval uh was kind of one of
the first eval doing that. Um and
despite being much cheaper than uh than
chatbot arena, it had really high
correlation
um spearman correlation with with
chatbot arena. So uh using our lamps can
be really good as like a as a judge for
for
uh for judging your performance and for
evaluating your performance. Um yeah so
it costed like running out like right
now probably cost much less but the time
uh was less than three minutes and and
less than $10.
Um
great. Okay. So I think I'm I'm getting
at the end. I do want to tell you a
little bit about systems and infra
because as I said um if you really
understand kind of the the uh the the
fact that scaling is what matters um
then the natural question then like the
natural thing that you should be
spending time on is is also like making
sure that your models your training can
scale well. Um so
uh yeah so the problem is that everyone
is balling by compute. Um so one idea
that you might have is like well if
you're balling by comput and if you know
that spending more compute uh gives you
a better answer why just not buying more
GPUs and and training on that. Um there
are a few reasons why we can do that.
One of course GPUs are are expensive but
they're not only expensive they are
scarce. So even if you have the money uh
it can be hard to just get access to the
best GPUs. And then there are physical
limitations. Um so if you have a lot of
GPUs you need to have the communication
between GPUs and that is uh that can
really slow down your training. Uh so
you do do need to kind of optimize uh
your systems and make sure that like
train training is is uh is as efficient
as possible on every GPU that you have.
Um
so yeah you need to do some good
resource allocation and you need to
optimize your pipelines.
Okay. So I will try to give you an
extremely brief overview of GPUs just
for you to get a sense of what matters
when you optimize uh these runs and uh
what you're actually optimizing for. Uh
so systems 101 uh GPUs. So the the
difference between GPUs and CPUs is that
essentially GPUs are massively parallel.
Uh so they will apply the same
instructions on uh in parallel on all uh
different threads but different inputs.
So you will have the same input that
will go on different threads and it will
basically uh sorry different inputs that
will go through different threads and
will be uh will apply the same
instructions to them. Uh so really the
difference with CPUs that you're
optimizing for throughput it's massively
parallel. So here you see GPUs and CPUs
the difference um
the so yeah as I said first GPUs are
massively parallel. Second thing is that
GPUs are really optimized for matrix
multiplications. Uh so GPUs are um
graphical processing units um and
graphical uh anything about computer
vision and graphics uh really requires
extremely fast matrix multiplications.
So from from kind of the early days of
GPUs um uh people were really optimizing
or like the the GPU um people building
GPUs are really optimizing uh for matrix
multiplication. So they have specific
cores uh that will uh make matrix
multiplication very fast um and actually
around 10 times faster than most uh
other floating point operations. Uh so
here you see different versions of GPUs
um and you see and you see kind of the
speed and you see that for matrix
multiplication is much faster uh
especially recently much faster than um
than non-matrix multiplication uh
floating point operations. Um so another
thing that is important to understand
about GPUs is that actually compute is
not the bottleneck anymore. So what I
mean by that is that if you look at um
here kind of the the compute that
uh peak like the peak hardware scaling.
So uh here you have compute so flops um
that that could be performed uh on the
the best hardware um across time. And
here you have uh basically the the
communication and um memory and how it
improved across time. And you see that
basically compute increased or improved
much better uh much faster sorry across
time than uh memory and communication.
So what that means is that right now we
have more compute in the GPU than we
have like memory and then we have
improvements in in uh in communication.
So in other words uh what the the
bottleneck uh for GPUs is not performing
the computation but it's actually
keeping the processor that performs the
computation fed up with data. So you
basically need to send as much data as
possible there and it's it's the
bottleneck is actually feeding the data
not doing the computation. That's a very
important thing to understand when
you're optimizing your your pipelines.
Um and uh yeah as as a result uh if you
look at uh this this paper from like
2020 that analyzes uh where you perform
all the compute from how much time takes
uh it takes to to run a transformer you
will actually see that things like uh
tensor contraction which is basically
matrix multiplication requires most of
the flops. So most of the most of the
actual compute uh that is required is
for for matrix multiplication but in
terms of runtime speed uh this is
actually pretty it's still majority but
it's only twothird of the runtime is is
spent on the thing that's that is most
of the compute and things like um
element element wise operation or like
some normalization actually requires
very little floating point operations
but requires a pretty large amount of uh
uh of time or basically you spend a lot
of time there because you need to still
like send to the GPUs your um your data
and do the computation even if the
computation is slow.
Okay. And the last thing that you need
uh to know um about about GPUs is that
there's a really a large memory kind of
hierarchy. Um so the closer you are to
the cause, the cause being the the
things that actually perform the
computation, the faster your the faster
the communication with the course will
be uh but the less memory there will be
there. Um and the further you from the
course, the more memory but the slower
and and you basically have like
different levels of of hierarchy. So you
have this uh this shed memory um and
then the L1 cache that is shed memory
that is super close and then you have
the L1 cache, the L2 cache and then you
have the global memory that is very far
from your your registers and and your um
uh yeah your processes.
So uh yeah this memory hierarchy and the
metric that we try to optimize when we
uh when we try to optimize our runs um
and uh just our our systems uh is model
flop utilization. You will often hear
this word um or MFU for short and this
is basically the ratio between the
observed throughput uh to your model and
kind of the theoretical best. So like
Nvidia will tell you at best we can do
that amount of flops. Um and and then
you you will check like how much you are
achieving and if you achieve uh MFU of
one that means you are able to get all
the data the maximum of data uh you can
always keep your processor basically fed
with data. Um so at any point of time
there's something that is uh being
computed um on on your processor. Uh
just to give you a rough uh sense of
these numbers, if you have 50% you're in
a really really really good shape. Um
and uh even big companies might might be
optimizing to go like higher than 15 or
20% and to achieve like this this 50%.
Great. So I want to give you a very
quick overview of like things that you
might want to do for optimizing your
runs. Um just to give you a sense of
like at least like things that people do
for optimizing kind of this this uh this
compute and making sure that your your
runs are scalable. Um one thing that you
might do is low precision low precision
uh uh um operations. So the idea is that
if you use fewer bits uh for every data
points or for every for every uh data
that goes in your u your processor you
will have faster communication and low
memory consumption. Um so as I said
given that the bottleneck is not the
compute but it's kind of this memory and
this communication you might just
decrease uh the precision uh in which
you put your data in and as a result you
will just have faster communication
because you can put more through the
ball like and lower memory consumption.
Um so for example for deep learning the
actual kind of decimal decimal precision
is not that that important except for a
few operations. uh that's because
there's a lot of noise in any case in
when you do uh when you train deep
neural networks um because of of uh
stocastic gradient descent already has a
lot of noise um so matrix
multiplications will will usually be
done in BF-16 um rather than FP32 so you
can half the precision and if you have
the precision uh what you can do so
usually like one thing that is very
common is using automatic mix precision
or AM during training uh which is that
The weights are stored in FP32. So use
32 um bits uh sorry bytes. Um but before
you compute uh before sorry before the
computation you will convert uh uh the
FP32 to BF-16. So you will basically
half the precision um and then
everything will be done in BF16. So you
will have less memory, you will have
more speed speed up because faster
communication um and your gradients will
be stored in in BF-16. So you'll have
memory gains and then at the end uh you
will put it back in FP32 and like this
uh every every like small operation that
you do uh can be can be shown in your
weights uh at pretty uh at pretty um
high precision.
Great. Um there are other optimization
for example operation uh operator um
operation fusion. So again the the idea
here is that communication is slow as we
said um and every time that you for
example if you you write in PyTorch
every time you you write a new line it
actually moves your variable back to
global memory. Um and that makes it very
costly because basically if you do
something like x1 is equal to x um the
cosine of x you will basically read from
x uh sorry read x from global memory
write it to x1 and then when you do this
new line x2 is equal x1 cosine of x1 you
will again take it back to global memory
and write it to x2. Um so that can be
that can be re very slow um because you
have a lot of this communication between
global and memory. Um
and so what you
might want to do so this is just to give
you a a schematic version of what is
happening. Uh so here you have
everything in memory your DRAM uh and
basically uh you will send uh data to
your processes for performing compute
and after every new line you will send
it back uh to your DRAM and then you
have to do it again and do it again. So
this is kind of the naive way if you
just have a pietorch function this is a
naive way that things are working. Um
but there's a much better way of of
doing that once you realize that the
communication is the bottleneck is that
you might just communicate once and do
all the operations and then communicate
it back. Uh so this is what fuse kernels
are doing. So the idea is that you
communicate once you perform all the
operations that you want and then you
send it back. And as we said this is
actually fast this is slow. So there are
fewer slow things here.
Um and this is basically what torch
compile uh does um to your code is that
it kind of fuses operations together.
Okay. Um tiling uh I'll I know it's
becoming long so I'll just quickly talk
through that. Um the idea is that the
order uh the the order yeah the order in
which you perform operation will matter
a lot because of uh of communication. Um
so what I mean by that is that you can
group and order threads that are
performing um some some communic some uh
computation to minimize the number of
times that you will communicate with
global memory. Uh so I'll give you an
example for matrix multiplication. Um
here this is the very naive way of doing
matrix multiplication where this is how
you basically learn it at school where
you take two matrices that you multiply
them. you will basically go through all
this column and all this row. You will
basically multiply these two together
and um multiply these numbers and then
sum across all of that and you get the
this number for this one. And the way
that this that the basically the memory
is accessed here is that one thread, one
thread here is going to access uh this
one and this one and then this one and
this one. And you'll basically have one
thread that is that is working with all
of this and then all of this one. Um and
then you will have another thread that
is working on these things uh separately
and then this when this one is done it
will work on a different column and a
different row. Um
so you will what is important here is
that you will rarely have uh you will
rarely re reread the same values uh from
from from cache. Uh in contrast, what
you can do is you can split up your
matrix multiplication into different
tiles to reuse memory. Um so for
example, you might say, well, I'm going
to have one uh thread that instead of
working with all the column and all the
the row at once, um it basically works
with all of these four uh values
together against these four values
together. So you basically do uh
multiply this and this together and then
this one and this one together and then
basically once you're um this one sorry
uh it's a bit hard to explain without
without actually showing it to you and
just with this this diagram but
basically this number here n 000 will be
used twice will be used to multiply m00
0 and m10.
So basically uh for one number that I
have access to I made two operations. Uh
so I have n 000 I made two operations.
So basically I have to read less from
global memory because by one read I made
two operations. While before with one
read I made only one operation. Um, so
you're basically making sure that you
make more work uh with with uh with the
same amount of data or or more sorry um
or same amount of work with with less
data. So you basically read less um and
you can still work through an algorithm
like this where you multiply uh these
element wise with this and then you have
another thread that works with this one
element Y with this one and then you
have the partial sums and you sum them
together. Anyways, all this to say it's
not super important. Um the the actual
kind of algorithm is really not that
important. What is important is that the
order in which you perform operations
can really impact um or like the
grouping and ordering can really impact
um the the number of times that you have
to read from global memory. And tiling
is one way where you basically group
things together in a single thread such
that with less data you can do more
computation.
Uh so you can kind of reuse these these
uh uh yeah reuse the reads and and
basically have access to your cache.
Um great. So flash attention is one
pretty famous uh um optimization that
was done for making attention faster and
it basically kind of combined the three
things that we talked about before which
is this kernel fusion uh the styling uh
and also one additional thing which is
recomputation. So sometimes actually
it's cheaper
sometimes it's cheaper to uh redo a
computation uh than actually reading uh
from your memory the values uh from so
so basically uh here the recmputation of
attention is is the idea that like don't
save everything sometimes it's easier to
just recomputee the values than like
storing them um and flash attention v1
got uh 1.7 end to end speed up um from
uh from tree uh 1.7x speed up gains just
by combining these things together. So
all this to say that um yeah systems
really matters. You can get huge speed
up gains at no m this is a completely ML
neutral. This is just an kind of an
order of operation um in yeah the order
in which you perform operation can
really improve a lot your performance.
Okay. Um
I think I'm arriving at the end. I do
want to maybe briefly talk about
paralization. That's kind of the last
big topic in terms of systems. Um so the
idea is that you have very big model.
This is one of the big problem is that
you have very big models and big models
cannot fit on one GPU. Um so you really
want to use as many GPUs as possible uh
for making your training runs uh fast.
So once you think about it this way,
there's a question of like how do you
split your GPUs? Uh sorry, how do you uh
how do you work with as many GPUs as
possible? Um and how do you fit your
model into into GPUs? And the idea is
that you can split your memory and your
computation across GPUs. So again, kind
of the problem is that models are big.
They don't fit across GPUs. Uh they
don't fit on a single GPU. Two, uh you
want results as fast as possible. you
want to put as many GPUs as possible
working together and the idea is that
you can kind of split the computation
and split the memory across different
GPUs and this is this is uh all about
parallelization.
Um, okay. Slight background here is to
naively train a par model that has P
parameters, you actually need 16 times P
gigabytes of D RAM. Um so
the reason uh the reason is that you
need uh four P uh so four bytes uh
because here we assume it's a uh 32
um floating like yeah FP32 so you have
four uh four bytes for uh every P
parameter um and so you have four yeah
sorry four p gigabytes for model
weights. Uh then for the optimizer, if
you talk about Adam, uh you need to
store both the mean and the variance of
uh of every par uh um every parameter.
So the optimizer needs to store two
times 4p gigabytes um in terms of
values. And so you have here 12 and here
you have 4 p for the gradient. So you
need to solve both the forward um sorry
both the weights and uh during when you
do back propagation you need to solve
the gradients and this is also 4. So
basically that means that for training a
7 billion parameter model you actually
need 112 gigabytes of memory uh which is
which is really um yeah which is really
huge.
Uh so the idea here is that you can
optimize that um by
by uh yeah the goal at least is to use
more GPUs um and and and to optimize uh
your training. So let's say that you
have um four GPUs here uh and you want
to uh optimize you want to basically
have every GPU working simultaneously on
uh on um on your data set. Uh one naive
way that you can do it is that you can
you can copy the model and the optimizer
on every GPU. you can split the data and
then you can basically have every GPU
working on a different uh on different
of uh on the same model but different
set of data uh because you split up your
data and then at the end after they they
do one step you basically communicate
the gradients and sum the gradients and
and that will be the the the total
gradient that you would have gotten if
you had actually trained on the four
sets of data of data.
So basically after every batch you
everyone works on a on a on a separate
batch and then at the end you get
gradients you communicate you sum them
um and then you have basically the same
gradient as what you would have had uh
had you trained on four times the batch
size. Um so the benefit is that now you
can use all these GPUs uh because now
you can use four times more GPUs uh than
before. Uh so it's four times faster
than before. Uh the the negative aspect
is that here you have literally no
memory gates because now
uh if if your model for example didn't
fit on one GPU, it still doesn't fit on
a single GPU right now. Uh so you and
also here we said 7B models require like
122 GB uh of memory. Here it means that
you really need to have 112 GB of memory
on every GPUs. So there's no memory
gains. Um so how would you split like
how would you split memory? How would
you get memory gains? Um, one way of
doing that is to
uh uh have each GPU update a subset of
weights. Um,
uh, yeah, update a subset uh of weights
and and and hold the subset of weights
uh and then you communicate them uh
before uh before updating your weights.
So this is what we call sharding. Um so
here we this is uh this is one way of
doing that is this paper called zero.
So here you see the baseline which has
uh the the 4p uh parameter um 4p
gigabytes for parameters. Here you have
the 4p gigabytes for gradients and here
you have the 8p gigabytes uh for
optimizer states. Um and they have
different levels of sharding. So you can
sh the first thing that you can shard is
you can shard the optimizer. So you can
say well every
GPU
will only have one subset of uh of
optimizer states and basically each of
them contain a subset and will just like
communicate them um uh when needed. Uh
so you basically have this and then you
can do the same thing. So this will cut
a lot uh your memory requirement from
120 gigabytes to 31 uh gigabytes. So
nearly a 4x decrease and then you can do
the same thing for your gradients and
you can do the same thing for your
parameters. So you can basically say
every GPU takes care of a different
subset of uh a different subset of
weights.
Um
okay so that was for data parallelism
and now let's talk about model
parallelism. Um the problem with data
parallelism is that it requires uh your
data to uh it requires to have at least
as much data as you have or at least as
much batch size as you have GPUs. Um so
so basically as I said is assume you
have a batch size of 16. Basically what
you're saying is if you have four GPUs
you have four uh every GPU now gets a
batch size of four. So 16 divided by 4.
Um, but what if I want to use 32 GPUs?
Like how do I now split up that data to
fit into 32 GPUs? The idea is that you
can have every GPU take care of applying
specific uh parameters rather than
updating. So what what we saw before
with this data paralism is that every
GPU can take care of updating specific
parameters. Um but here the idea is um
with model paralism is that instead of
having every GPU taking care of um uh of
updating the parameters you can you can
have every GPU taking care of applying
the parameters. So like applying the the
actual uh operations.
So for example in pipeline parallelism
you can say that every GPU has access to
a whole different layer. So you can say
layer one is on GPU 1, layer two is on
GPU 2. And basically what you have is
that once you predict um sorry once you
take data you you make all the data pass
to your first layer which is on GPU one
and then you send it to GPU 2 it passes
through the second layer and GPU 3 etc.
Um so uh uh yeah so this is for pipeline
parallel. I'm going to skip that part.
And then you have tensor parallel. Uh so
this is the idea that instead of of
splitting um instead of having every GPU
hold a different layer, you could have
every uh you can kind of split matrices
or you can split inside of a layer you
can split between GPUs. Um so for
example when you apply when you multiply
uh two matrices sorry when you multiply
a matrix with a vector what you can do
is you can split up the matrix into two
can split up the vector into two and you
can basically say I'm going to operate
with these matrices on this vector and
let's meet these matrices on this vector
and then I'm going to aggregate
everything at the end together. So this
is what we call tensor paral tensor
paralism. So pipeline paralism is this
idea that every layer has every GPU has
different layers. tensor palism
basically split up the weights into
different GPUs. Um,
great. Okay. And the last uh last
example for system optimization is that
models are really huge. Uh so instead of
kind of splitting up your model onto uh
model weights onto different uh
different GPUs what you can have is uh
you can say well actually not every data
point has to go through every parameter
and this is what we call sparsity. So a
very common uh architecture that is
sparse is the mixture of experts that
basically says um only some parameter
will be active for some types of of data
sets. um some sometimes of data points.
So the idea is that you now have a data
point um that that comes in and it will
only go to some set of hyper some set of
parameters not all the parameters and
this makes it very easy for for doing
multi kind of for doing paralism and
like multiGPU training because you can
just have different GPUs contain the
parameters that are required for
different uh different data points. Um
so here you have a dense model that
basically this is a kind of inside a
little bit too much maybe into the weeds
but if you know about transformers uh
you have this like linear layer at some
point and you can basically say the
linear layer is going to be split into
like different linear layers and
different data points will go through
different linear layers and every GPU
can basically have access to different
uh different linear layers. Um so if you
didn't follow kind of the last two sides
though um maybe a little bit not as
important but what I do want to stress
is that there's a lot of work that goes
into uh systems optimization and kind of
optimiz uh optimizing the use of your
compute and uh the different ways that
we saw uh about doing that was tiling so
like ordering of your operations. Uh it
was um uh the the the sparsity. So
basically making your model um uh sparse
and not having every every parameter
sorry every data point go through every
parameter. We talked about parallelism.
So basically using more GPUs um and uh
yes I think that's basically it. Great.
Um so we're done. Uh there's no
questions today because as I said this
is a re-recording of uh of the video. I
know this was uh pretty um
pretty long. I'm also starting to be a
little bit a little bit tired, but uh I
hope it was uh useful and um yeah, good
luck for the rest of the class.